So we've talked about Composition API,
we talked about Script Setup.
Now we need to talk about something called Composable.
This is the new kid on the block when it comes to view because it's
basically a view-specific terminology around
a type of reusable JavaScript utility that
uses the Composition API, hence why it's called Composable.
So for those coming from a React background,
you might be familiar with the React hooks
where they prefix everything with use,
like use mouse position, that kind of thing.
That pattern has also carried over into view in that we will
basically, I'm going to be demoing this shortly,
but we'll be able to create some helper,
basically utility functions using the Composition API,
and then this is the elusive,
how do we share some stuff between components
without polluting and rewriting the same thing?
Composables are your answer for that.
Okay, so let's load up the counter real quick.
So I'm going to go inside of my app.view,
and this time we're going to practice this.
I'm actually just going to import my base counter,
and this is from base counter here.
We're going to delete that,
and then we're just going to render out our base counter,
just like that.
Okay, so there you go.
Also, script setup in the flesh, right there.
Okay, we have the ability to increment, that's fine,
but what if we wanted the ability to count in other places?
This is basically like an encapsulated functionality
that we don't want to,
so when we're looking at this functionality,
again, this is a simplistic example,
but for the sake of understanding composables,
imagine if we wanted the count to be managed
from multiple places.
In other words, at base counter,
it's nice that it has it here,
but what if we wanted the base,
let's say inside of user card,
what if user card wanted the ability
to also increment the count?
At the moment, you'd have to duplicate that,
it's kind of tricky,
you would have to probably do some props
to have your app manage that,
but count is something that really,
if we think about it,
it really does belong in base counter as a state,
but it really doesn't make sense to put it at the app level
because the app usually cares about a bunch of other things.
So what do we have?
We have composables, how does that work?
Well, let's start by creating a folder called composables,
which is what you'll see a lot in code bases
these days for view three.
And what we're gonna do is we're gonna create
inside of that composables,
I'm gonna create something called a count,
I'll just call it a count store,
because that's what I wanted to do,
I want to basically store what's going on with count.
So I'll split this over with two columns,
you can see what's going on.
And so here, what we really wanna do
is we want this piece of data,
let's start simple, let's make that shared,
so that we can show that in multiple places.
The way you do that is we're gonna import a ref,
well actually no, we're gonna reverse engineer that
a little bit easier.
For those who are new to JavaScript modules,
this might seem a little bit intimidating,
but we're gonna basically build it up from scratch.
When you have a JavaScript file that you wanna import
into another file, the main thing you need to do
is have them to export, right?
So normally you would have an export,
like count of 10, like this, okay?
Actually, so let's make it a hundred, like this.
And then what we could do is you could then say,
import a count store, or actually import,
we'll destructure this part,
from composable slash count store.
And what are we, we're taking out of that,
we're taking the count out of this.
And actually, let's make this new count
so that visually it's easier for you all
to see what's going on here.
And then what we can do here is inside of our setup method,
we could say, ah yes, we're gonna go ahead and say,
return new count.
Okay, so to show you what just happened here,
we just wrote a standard JavaScript,
whoop, what's going on?
Do, do, do, do, fail to resolve, import,
composables, count store.
You could have back up one.
Oh, back up one level, yep, file name, that's it.
Great call.
And then to show that this works,
we're gonna render this on the page.
H2, new count.
You can see, we successfully wrote a little piece
of JavaScript that's now reusing two places.
Now again, to prove that this works,
again, let's continue proving this out,
is that we will then import the same new count
on user card.
Similarly, we'll use a setup method in here.
I'm not gonna spend the time to convert everything
right now, just to kind of make the process
a little bit easier.
But we're gonna return new count here.
And then we can actually then, as an H2,
also do new count.
So inside of the user card,
what we're gonna do now is also display new count,
so we can actually prove that this was successfully
imported in two places.
But we need this to actually render on the page.
So we need to go to app.view,
and let's go ahead and bring in our user card.
Although I'm actually saying,
oh yeah, user card is correct, there we go, perfect.
So user card here.
But I believe user card had some props though,
didn't require some props, it did.
Object for name and food, that's fine,
we can do that real quick.
This will be a user,
with a name of Ben,
and we'll just stick food,
this time we'll do cheeseburger,
although I did do that earlier.
So for the sake of doing something new,
we're just gonna do ramen, safe.
Boom, okay.
So you can see now, 100 appears here in the count,
100 appears here at the bottom.
So we can verify that once more by going to count store,
changing this to 200,
and if you can see and refresh,
you'll see that it's updating,
but again, this is a constant, it's kind of weird.
All right, so this is cool,
but once again,
we want the ability to be able to change it.
So let's go inside of our base counter,
and this time we can,
well, what might you do instinctively?
We might go, well, instead of this,
we'll say this.newCount,
and when we click on it,
we want newCount to also get incremented as well,
and we'll increment it by 10.
So we'll save that, we'll refresh, we'll hit it,
and you'll notice, oh, it's kind of working.
This is kind of weird,
but then you'll notice that it's working in this context,
but it's not working in this context,
and this is a little bit of a preview
of the kind of UI bugs that we had to deal with over time
as developers were dealing with reactive state changes,
and this is what a lot of the frameworks do well for us.
So here's the deal.
What we want to do is, what do we want to do?
We want to make this a reactive reference
that view will contract.
So what do we do?
Import ref from view.
Wrap this in a ref, save, fresh, everything's connected.
And just like that,
you have this little JavaScript file,
which is the one variable you care about,
shared across two different components at different levels,
and everything's updating as you would expect.
And so this pattern here that we're seeing
regarding the combination of a setup
with importing whatever you're dropping in
is one that I would say is probably gonna be seen more
in options API,
and that's why we spend so much time in composition API
in that I would say going forward
as architectures continue to evolve,
composition API will become more and more popular in view apps.
This is not to say that it is the one true right way
and that you have to write your apps this way.
It's just it's a very effective technique,
and to try to ignore it for the sake of ignoring it
doesn't really make a lot of sense.
So for those of us who still love options API,
just sprinkle it in just like this,
and then you get the benefits of composing together
different pieces of functionality
that you can reuse in your options,
but then you can still get the benefits of options.
For those of us who want to use composition API fully,
then it really is just as simple as importing the thing
and then using it.